1900년대 초까지 볼츠만은
견디기 힘든 싸움을 계속했습니다
But by the beginning of the 1900s, the struggle was getting too hard for him.
그는 우주의 가장 근본적인
작동 원리 중 하나를 밝혀냈고
Boltzmann had discovered one of the fundamental equations
which makes the universe work, and he had dedicated his life to it.
그것에 평생을 바쳤습니다
철학자 버트랜드 러셀은
이렇게 말했습니다
The philosopher Bertrand Russell said that "For any great thinker.."
"만물이 이러한 근본 법칙에 따라
흘러간다는 사실의 발견은.."
"..this discovery that everything flows from these fundamental laws comes.."
"..높은 사고력의 소유자라면 누구에게나
압도적인 힘으로 깨달음을 준다."
as he described it, "..with the overwhelming force of a revelation, .."
"마치 이탈리아의 언덕을 오르는
등반객의 눈에.."
"..like a palace emerging from the autumn mist, .."
"..가을 안개가 걷히며 드러나는
궁전의 모습처럼."
"..as the traveler ascends the Italian hillside."
볼츠만도 그랬습니다
And so it was for Boltzmann.
그러나 그에겐 이곳
이탈리아 뒤노가 그 궁전이었습니다
But for him, that palace was here at Duino in Italy,
그가 목을 매 자살한 곳입니다
where he hung himself.
1906년 볼츠만은 아내와 딸과 함께
휴가차 이곳 뒤노에 왔습니다
In 1906, Boltzmann came here to Duino with his wife and daughter on holiday,
그의 이론은 여전히 외면받았으며,
그는 지치고 심약해진 상태였죠
.. exhausted and demoralized, his ideas still not accepted.
그는 아내와 딸이 산책 나간 사이에
유서도 남기지 않고 자살했습니다
While they were out walking he killed himself and left no note of explanation.
볼츠만의 생각을 알 길은 없지만,
짐작은 할 수 있습니다
Of course we can never know what Boltzmann was thinking, but I think we have clues.
그는 경이로운 발상을 이해하는 것의
무게감을 잘 알고 있었죠
Boltzmann knew what it was to be in the grip of a beautiful and powerful idea.
이런 말도 했습니다,
"만가(挽歌)를 읊는 시인과도 같이.."
He once wrote that "What is the poet laments holds for the mathematician.."
"..나는 피를 토하는 심정으로
수학을 연구한다."
".. that he writes his works with the blood of his heart."
그가 열정적인 사람이었음을
엿볼 수 있죠
So we know that he was a passionate man.
또다른 추측도 해 봅니다
But I think there is another clue.
볼츠만의 주요 논문 중 하나에서
At the start of one of Boltzmann's major scientific papers
그는 괴테의 '파우스트'에 나오는
세 문장을 인용하고 있습니다
he quotes three lines from Goethe's 'Faust'.
"진리를 찾아내어라. 그것을 분명하게 기록하라.
목숨을 걸고 그 진리를 지켜라."
"Bring forth what is true. Write it so it's clear. Defend it to your last breath."
바로 그 자신이 한 일이죠
.. which of course of he does.
그런데, 이런 생각이 듭니다
But I think there's something deeper here.
과학 논문 첫머리에 왜 하필
파우스트를 인용했을까요?
Why quote 'Faust' at the start of a scientific paper?
파우스트와 악마가 맺은
계약의 내용은
The pact that Faust makes with the Devil
파우스트가 원하는 모든 지식과 경험을
악마가 제공하는 대신
is that the devil will give him of all of the knowledge and all of the experience that he wants,
파우스트는 어느 한 순간에도
영원히 머무를 수 없다는 것입니다
(가장 행복한 순간에 시간을 멈춰달라고 말하면
악마가 파우스트의 영혼을 가져가겠다는 계약)
so long as he never asks to stay in any one moment.
제 생각에는, 볼츠만이
30년간의 힘든 투쟁 뒤에
And I think when Boltzmann came here to this beautiful place
이 아름다운 곳을 찾아와서는
after thirty years of fighting for what he believed in,
이렇게 말하지 않았을까요?
He simply said,
"바로 지금 완벽하고 아름다운 순간에
머무르고 싶도다."
(파우스트가 악마를 불러내는 주문)
"I want to stay here in this perfect beautiful moment."
"여기서 떠나고 싶지 않다.
시간아, 이대로 멈추어다오."
(파우스트가 악마를 불러내는 주문)
"I don't want to have to leave. I want time for me to stop."
논란을 불러 일으킨
볼츠만의 위대한 업적은
The great and controversial thing that Boltzmann had done
변하지 않고 완벽한 고전 물리학에
was to introduce into the unchanging perfection of classical physics
흘러가는 시간, 비가역적인 변화라는
개념을 도입한 것입니다
the notion of real time, of irreversible change.
그랬던 그 자신이, 삶의 마지막 순간
'시간이 멈추기를' 바랐던 셈이죠
And yet it was this man, who in his final moments wanted time to stop.
아이러니하게도 볼츠만이 죽은 직후
그의 이론이 입증되었습니다
So ironically Boltzmann was vindicated just after his death.
조금만 더 기다렸더라면,
볼츠만은
If he would have waited a little longer, Boltzmann would have been
20세기 물리학 혁명의 아버지로
일컬어졌을 것입니다
one of the father of the revolutionary of the 20th century physics.
시대를 잘못 만난 삶처럼,
죽음도 때이른 것이었습니다
Yet Boltzmann died as he'd lived, out of step with his times.
그가 물리학에 불확실성이라는
씨앗을 뿌렸지만
He had sown the seeds of uncertainty in physics,
그것을 가꾼 사람은 없었습니다
but no school of followers took up his work.
차라리 그보다는,
Against all the odds it was Cantor, who had uncovered uncertainty in mathematics,
칸토어가 들춰낸 수학의 불확실성이
주목을 받았습니다
around whom followers were gathering.
새로운 세대의 수학자와 철학자들은
A new generation of mathematicians and philosophers were convinced
칸토어를 좌절시킨
문제와 역설을 해결한다면
if only they could solve the problems and paradoxes that had defeated Cantor
수학은 다시금 완벽해질 것이라고
자신했습니다
math could be made perfect again.
그중 가장 유명한 인물인
힐베르트는 이렇게 선언했습니다
The most prominent amongst them, Hilbert, declared
"인류 지성의 자존심을
지키기 위해서라도.."
"The definitive clarification of the nature of the infinite.."
"..반드시 무한의 본질을
명확하게 밝혀내야만 한다"
"..has become necessary for the honour of human understanding itself."
그들은 확실성을
집요하게 추구한 나머지,
They were so concerned to find some kind of certainty,
논리적이며 증명 가능한 것들만이
they'd come to believe that the only kind of understanding
진정으로 이해할 가치가
있다고 믿었습니다
that was really worth anything was the logical and the provable.
완벽한 논리와 추론 체계를
찾으려는 노력이
And a measure of how desperate this attempt to find
얼마나 필사적이었는지 보여주는
좋은 예가 여기 있습니다
the perfect system of reasoning and logic had become is this.
1910년에 씌어진
세 권으로 된 '수학 원리'입니다
(by 러셀 & 화이트헤드)
Three volumes of the 'Principia Mathematica' published in 1910.
이 책은 상당히 많은
분량을 할애하여..
It takes a huge chunk of this volume..
1 + 1 = 2 를
증명하고 있습니다
just to prove that 1 + 1 = 2.
또한 그 증명의 상당 부분은
유한과 무한의 문제,
And a large part of that proof revolves around the problems of the finite and the infinite
그리고 칸토어가 포기했던
역설들을 논하고 있습니다
and the paradoxes that Cantor's work had thrown up.
그러나 '수학 원리'의
노력에도 불구하고,
But despite the 'Principia',
논리와 수학에는
이미 금이 가 버렸으며
there was now the feeling that the logic of math had undone itself
"이게 다 칸토어 때문이다"라는
생각이 팽배해졌습니다
and it was Cantor's fault.
오스트리아의 작가 뮤질이
표현했던 바와 같이
As the Austrian writer Musil wrote at the time,
수학자들은 어느날 갑자기,
이론의 토대가 되는 어떤 주춧돌이
suddenly mathematicians, those working in innermost region, discovered that
절대로 제자리에 놓일 수
없다는 것을 알아챘습니다
something in the foundations could absolutely not be put in order.
바닥을 살펴본 뒤, 사실은 모든게
사상누각이었음을 알았습니다
Indeed, they took a look at the bottom and found that the whole edifice was standing on air.
칸토어는 수학과 논리의 한계를
끝까지 몰고 간 대가를 치렀습니다
Cantor had stretched the limits of math and logic to breaking point, and paid for it.
삶의 마지막 20년 대부분은
정신병원을 드나들며 보냈습니다
Much of the last twenty years of his life were spent in and out of the asylum.
칸토어가 할레의 네르펜클리닉에
마지막으로 온 것은 1917년입니다
The last time that Cantor came here to the Nervenklinik in Halle was in 1917.
그는 이곳을 끔찍이 싫어했고
And he truly did not want to be here.
제발 자기를 꺼내달라고
아내에게 편지를 쓰기도 했습니다
He wrote to his wife begging her to let him come home.
이곳엔 그를 포함해
민간인은 두 명 뿐이었고
He was one of only two civilians left here.
나머지는 1차대전의
사상자들이었습니다
The rest of the place was filled with the casualties of World War I.
1918년 1월 6일
But on the 6th January 1918, the greatest mathematician of his century died alone in his room,
이 당대 최고의 수학자는
병실에서 외로이 세상을 떴습니다
그의 야심찬 계획을
미완으로 남겨둔 채..
his great project still unfinished.
칸토어가 빼낸 조약돌은 언젠가
산사태를 일으킬 수도 있었습니다
Cantor had dislodged the pebble, which would one day start a landslide.
그는, 신은 모든 생각을 통합하고
역설조차 해결할수 있다고 보았습니다
For him, it had all been held together, the paradoxes resolved, in God.
그런데 신이 죽어버렸다면
어떻게 해야 합니까..
But what holds our ideas together, when God is dead?
신이 없다면,
산사태는 피할 수 없습니다
Without God, the pebble is dislodged and the avalanche is unleashed.
그리고 1차대전에서 신은 죽었습니다
And World War I had killed God.
마침내 손에서 미끄러져 나갑니다
Here at last was the slippage.
서양의 역사를 보면, 우리는 줄곧
확실성을 갈구해 오지 않았습니까
Hasn't there always been a desire in history of the West to find certainty
루이스 새스 - 임상심리학자, 럿거스 대학
설령 옛날에는 그러한 열망이
더 적었다 할지라도, 그 이유는
or maybe there wasn't so much desire at earlier eras
우리 곁엔 이미 확실성, 즉 신이라는
존재가 있다고 가정했기 때문입니다
because the assumption was that we had that - there was God.
회의주의로 무장한
데카르트*마저도
* '방법적 회의'에 의한 진리 추구를 주창
And even Descartes, despite all of his skepticism,
아무런 문제의식 없이
신의 존재를 당연시했습니다
assumes for him unproblematically that there is God.
그러니, 이른바 '신의 죽음'
이후에는 대체 어떻게 될 것인가
So what happens when that really comes into question
..하는 물음이 제기됩니다
after 'the death of God' so to speak.
신이 죽음에 따라,
인간이 작은 부분을 차지했던
And along with the death of God is a loss of faith in some
초자연적 질서에 대한 믿음도
사그라지게 됩니다
supernatural order of which we are small part.
1차대전은 모두가 패자였습니다
No one won the Great War.
베르사이유 조약*은 휴전이었을 뿐
아무것도 해결하지 못했습니다
* 1차대전 후 강화조약
Nothing was resolved at Versailles. It was merely an armistice.
전쟁 전에 불거진 학문적 위기도
여전히 해결되지 않았습니다
And none of the intellectual crisis that preceded it had been resolved either.
'수학 원리' 같은 것도 그저
임시방편에 지나지 않았습니다
Things like the 'Principia' had merely papered over the cracks.
'수학 원리'는 일면
베르사이유 조약과 비슷합니다
In a way the 'Principia' was like the Versailles Treaty, only a lot more substantial.
분량이 엄청나다는
차이가 있지만요
말하자면 시멘트 1만톤을 쏟아부어
수학에 생긴 균열을 메운것입니다
This is basically 10000 tons of intellectual concrete poured over the cracks in mathematics.
얼마간은 그렇게
잘 메워진듯 했습니다
And for a while it looked like it really might hold.
그런데 이 비엔나 대학 도서관에
한 젊은이가 찾아옵니다
But then a young man came here to the University of Vienna to this library.
쿠르트 괴델입니다
His name was Kurt Godel.
그가 이곳에서 한 연구는
And the work that he did here
완벽한 논리/추론 체계를 향한 꿈을
물거품으로 만들었습니다
brought that dream of finding the perfect system of reasoning and logic crashing down.
- 논리의 한계 -
괴델은 볼츠만이 죽은 해인
1906년 태어났습니다
Godel was born the year Boltzmann died - 1906.
불안정한 시대에 자라난 그는
쉴새없이 질문을 던지는 아이였고
He was an insatiably questioning boy, growing up in unstable times.
가족들은 그를
'미스터 와이(Mr. Why)'라 불렀죠
His family called him 'Mr. Why'.
그가 대학에 들어간 때는
1차대전이 끝난 뒤입니다
But by the time he went to university, World War I was over.
유럽과 마찬가지로
오스트리아는 불황기였으며
But Austria like the rest of Europe was in the grip of the depression
히틀러는 국가사회주의정당을
만들었습니다
and Hitler was forming the National Socialist Party.
그는 뛰어난 젊은 철학자, 정치이론가,
시인, 과학자 등의 모임인
Godel for his part became one of a brilliant group of young philosophers,
political thinkers, poets and scientists known as the 'Vienna Circle'.
'비엔나 서클'에 참여했습니다
혼란이 오히려 반가운 때였죠.
사상을 강요하는 중앙 권력이 없으니
Chaos was good, because it meant that there was no central authority
개개인의 아이디어들이
자랄 수 있죠
that was imposing ideas, so individuals could come up with their own ideas.
그런데 혼란은 한편으로는
자유를 가져다주기도 했지만
The chaos around them on the one hand had a liberating effect.
동시에 사람들은 확실한
관념을 찾아 헤매게 되었습니다
On the other hand, they were desperately searching for ideas that they could believe in
모든게 허무해 보이니까
because everything else around them was crumbling in a heap.
믿고 따를만한 멋진 생각들을
찾았던 거죠
So you want to find some beautiful ideas that you could believe in.
급진주의자, 혁명론자들도
주위에 있었지만
Though Godel was surrounded by radicals and revolutionary thinkers, he was not one himself.
괴델 자신은 그 부류에
속하지 않았습니다
그는 세상 물정에 무관심하고
꼼꼼한 사람이었으며
He was an unworldly and exact man
힐베르트처럼 수학이 언젠가는
완벽함을 되찾을거라 믿었습니다
who believed, like Hilbert, that math at least could be made whole again.
그러나 헛된 꿈이었죠
But it was not to be.
그는 힐베르트 프로그램*을
무너뜨릴 생각이 전혀 아니었습니다
* 수학의 모든 이론을 엄격하게 형식화하여
무모순의 완전한 체계를 완성하려던 시도
He certainly did not start out with trying to explode Hilbert's program also.
산술 체계의 완전성*을
증명하는 일이
* 어떤 이론 내의 모든 참인 명제가
증명이 가능한가 하는 성질
In fact, I think it came to Godel ultimately as a surprise
불가능하다는 사실을 깨달았을 때
그 자신도 놀랐을 것입니다
when he showed that its next step, to show the completeness of arithmetic, was unachievable.
순수 수학에서 아주 기괴한
일이 벌어진겁니다
There was actually something very mysterious happening in pure mathematics
블랙홀, 빅뱅, 양자적 불확정성
같은 것만큼이나 요상한..
in its own way as mysterious as black holes, as the big bang, as quantum uncertainty in the atom.
바로 괴델의 불완전성 정리입니다.
당시에는 미스테리였습니다
And this was Godel's incompleteness theorem. At that time, there was a mystery there.
다른건 몰라도 적어도
순수 논리의 세계에서는
The one place where you don't expect there to be mysteries is in pure reason..
애매모호함이 없으며
흑백이 분명하다고 여겨져 왔는데
this pure reason should be black and white, it should be really clear.
그러한 순수 논리에서
불분명한 부분이 드러난겁니다
But pure reason, the clearest thing there is, was revealing that there were things that were unclear.
비엔나 서클의 정기 모임이
열렸던 카페입니다
This is one of the cafes where the Vienna Circle used to meet regularly.
1930년 늦여름, 이 카페에서
괴델은 두 동료와 이야기하던 중
Late summer of 1930, Godel came to the cafe with two eminent colleagues.
자신이 연구하던 주제에 대해
잠깐 언급했습니다
Towards the end of the conversation, he just mentioned an idea he'd been working on,
'불완전성 정리'입니다
which he called the 'incompleteness theorem'.
그가 증명했다고 언급한 내용은
And what he told them, was that he had just proved
모든* 수리 논리 체계에는
한계가 있다는 것입니다
* 진행자는 줄곧 '모든'이라고 말하고 있는데
사실은 특정조건을 만족하는 체계에 대한 것임
that all systems of mathematical logic were limited,
참이지만 결코 증명이
불가능한 명제가
that there would always be some things, which while true,
반드시 존재한다는 것입니다
would never be able to be proved to be true.
불완전성 정리를 통하여
괴델이 증명한 것은
What Godel showed in his incompleteness theorem is that
공리들, 즉 논증의 토대를
아무리 크게 확장하더라도
no matter how large you make your basis of reasoning, your axioms, your set of axioms,
산술 체계에는 반드시, 참이지만
증명 불가능한 명제가 있다는 것입니다
in arithmetic there would always be statements that are true but cannot be proved.
아무리 많은 데이터를 가져와도
No matter how much data you have to build on,
참인 명제들 모두를 증명하는 것은
절대로 불가능합니다
you will never prove all true statements.
이로써 르네상스적인 이상,
What this meant was that the great Renaissance dream,
즉 언젠가 수학과 논리로
모든 진리를 증명하게 되어
that one day math and logic would be able to prove all things
신에 필적할 지식을 획득하리라는
꿈이 무너진 것입니다
and give us a God-like knowledge, that dream was over.
그런데 이 아이디어는
너무나 뜬구름잡는 것으로 보여서
But this idea was so far away from what anyone else was working on,
what anyone else even suspected,
이 동료들 누구도 괴델의 말을
이해하지 못했습니다
that neither of his colleagues understood what he had just told them.
비유하자면 폭탄이 터졌는데
그 여파를 아직 느끼지 못한거죠
It was as if there was an explosion but the blast wave hadn't hit them yet.
이튿날, 이제 수학계의
원로가 된 힐베르트는
Unaware of what had happened in the Cafe, the very next day,
카페에서 벌어진 일을 모른채
쾨니히스베르크 강연에서
Hilbert, now the 'grand old man' of mathematics stood up and gave a lecture in Konigsberg
이렇게 선언했습니다,
"우리는 알아야만 한다. 우리는 알게 될 것이다."
in which he said, "We must know. We will know."
공교롭게도, 그 바로 전날 괴델은
The irony was that the very day before
'우리가 절대로 알 수 없는'
것들이 있음을 증명했죠
Godel had proved that there were some things we would 'never' know.
이 결과를 언짢아하는
사람들도 있었습니다
Some didn't like it, some.. in particular for instance Hilbert.
힐베르트도 처음에는
대단히 화를 냈다고 합니다
It seemed that at the beginning he was quite annoyed and angry.
그런데 이것은
좋다 싫다의 문제가 아닙니다
This is not a matter of liking it or not. It is..
증명이 되었고,
받아들여야만 하는 것이죠
you have here this proof and.. one has to live with it.
괴델의 논증에 허점은 없었을까요?
Are there any holes in Godel's argument?
아뇨, 완벽한 증명입니다.
지극히 명료하고 명백한 논리입니다
No, there are not. This was a perfect argument. His argument was so crystal clear and obvious.
칸토어의 역설을 풀려고 노력한
힐베르트를 도우려다가
Godel had joined Hilbert in trying to solve the paradoxes uncovered by Cantor.
괴델은 그 노력이 결국
부질없는 것임을 증명했습니다
Instead, he had just proved that would never happen.
무한에 대한 칸토어의 연구에서
착안한 그의 연구 결과는
His work, springing directly from Cantor's work on infinity,
몇몇 역설들은 해결 불가능하며
더욱 많은 역설들이 있음을 보였습니다
proved the paradoxes were unsolvable and there would be more of them.
하지만 옳은 말을 했다고
꼭 평판까지 얻는 것은 아니죠
But being right didn't make him popular.
비엔나 대학 안마당에
다시 왔습니다
So here we are again in the great courtyard of Vienna University
수많은 석학들의 흉상들이 있죠
with the busts of all of the great thinkers
그러나 괴델은 없습니다
except for Kurt Godel. There's no bust to Godel here.
그런데 그 이유가 혹시
And I can't help but feel that at least part of the reason that he's not here
괴델의 연구에 대해 사람들이 가진
불편함 때문은 아니었을까요?
is simply due to the nature of his ideas.
제 생각에는, 괴델이 내놓은 결과를
흔쾌히 받아들이는 사람은 없습니다
Ah~ well you see nobody wants to face him.
In my opinion nobody wants to face the consequences of Godel.
수학자들은 어쨌거나 힐베르트 식으로
형식 체계를 밀고 나가려고 하죠
You see, basically people want to go ahead with formal systems anyway
and as if Hilbert had it all right.
괴델은 그러한 형식주의적* 관점을
파괴한 것입니다
* 수학을 형식적, 기계적 기호 조작으로 보는 견해.
앞서 말한 힐베르트 프로그램도 여기서 나옴
You see, and in my opinion Godel explodes that formalist view of mathematics,
정해진 공리로부터 기계적으로
정리를 찍어내면 된다는 시각을 말이죠
(이 말도 형식주의에 대한 설명임)
that you can just mechanically grind away on a fixed set of concepts.
괴델이 그러한 시도를
근본부터 흔들어놓았지만
So even though, I believe Godel pulled out the rug and from under him(???) intellectually
그 현실을 마주하는 것은
불편합니다
nobody wants to face that fact.
그러다보니, 괴델에 대한
애증이 교차합니다
So there's a very ambivalent attitude to Godel
그가 태어난지 100년이 지난 지금도
매우 이중적인 태도가 있습니다
even now a century after his birth.. very ambivalent attitude.
한편으로는 괴델을 역사상
가장 위대한 논리학자로 칭송하지만
On the one hand, he is the greatest logician of all time so logicians acclaim him,
또 한편으로는,
괴델이 가져온 결과에 대해
but on the other hand, they don't want people who are not logicians
모르던 사람은 모르고 넘어갔으면
싶어하는 면도 있습니다
to talk about the consequences of Godel's work
괴델이 한 말은 결국
논리학에 부족함이 있다는 거니까요
because the obvious conclusion from Godel's work is that logic is a failure,
외면하고 다른 주제로
넘어가고 싶어하죠
.. let's move onto something else, and this would destroy the field.
괴델 자신도 이 결론이 몰고 온
영향을 실감했습니다
Godel too felt the effects of his conclusion.
이 결과가 함축하는
진정한 의미를 파악해 가면서
As he worked out the true extent of what he had done
수학의 본질에 관한
괴델의 믿음도 깎여 나갔습니다
incompleteness began to eat away at his own beliefs about the nature of mathematics.
건강도 나빠졌고, 자신의
정신 상태까지 걱정되기 시작했죠
His health began to deteriorate and he began to worry about the state of his mind.
마침내 1934년
신경쇠약에 걸렸습니다
In 1934 he had his first breakdown.
다시 회복되었는가 했으나
문제는 더 커졌습니다
But it was after he recovered however that his real troubles began,
그는 중대한 결심을 했습니다
when he made a fateful decision.
불완전성 정리를 내놓은 직후부터
Almost as soon as Godel has finished the incompleteness theorem,
그는 중요한 미해결 난제에
착수했습니다
he decides to work on the great unsolved problem of modern mathematics,
칸토어의 연속체 가설이었죠
Cantor's continuum hypothesis.
그 영향을 한번 볼까요
And this is the effect that it has on him.
괴델이 썼던 연습장입니다
These are some pages from one of Godel's workbooks. And they all look like this.
보시다시피 깔끔하고 정연합니다
Beautifully neat. Beautifully logical.
반면 이걸 볼까요
Except for this one.
연속체 가설을 연구하면서
쓴 연습장입니다
This is the workbook where he is working on the continuum hypothesis.
괴델은 칸토어와 마찬가지로
이 문제를 풀지도, 내려놓지도 못했습니다
(하지만 괴델은 나중에 이 문제의
아주 중요한 진전을 이루었음)
Godel, like Cantor before him, could neither solve the problem nor put it down
상태가 점점 나빠졌는데도 말이죠
even as it made him unwell.
여기에는 개인적, 심리적 차원의
There could be a danger, and perhaps there is also a danger
위험성이 도사리고 있습니다
at the more ??? or personal, psychological level.
원래부터 지적 자기성찰이나
자의식이 과잉이 되기 쉬운
If you're a person who is already prone to a kind of exaggerated
그런 성향의 사람일수록,
intellectual self-reflection, self-consciousness,
학문 활동의 결과로
그런 경향이 더욱 심화되어
you may find that your intellectual work is, exaggerating, exacerbating that tendency
사는게 고달파질 수 있습니다
which of course could make life more difficult to live.
괴델은 이때가 인생에서
가장 불행한 때였다고 말했습니다
He calls this the worst year of his life.
그는 심각한 신경쇠약에 시달렸고
결국 요양소로 향했습니다
He has a massive nervous breakdown and ends up in a sanatorium
칸토어가 그랬듯이요
just like Cantor.
물론 이건 능력이 뛰어나고
We're talking about people here who of course are
극도로 추상적인
문제들에 천착하면서
capable of and maybe afflicted with the capacity to
자신을 잊어버릴 정도로
몰입하다 보니
care very very much about things that are very very abstract,
스스로를 괴롭히는
사람들의 얘기입니다
to lose themselves in their, in these intellectual problems.
이곳은 괴델이 지냈던
요양소들 가운데 하나인
One of the sanatoria that Godel spent some time in is here,
비엔나 외곽의
푸커스도르프 요양소입니다
the Purkersdorf Sanatorium just outside of Vienna.
정신병은 이성주의를 통해
치료할 수 있다는 것이
The Purkersdorf itself was built to embody the philosophy
이 요양소의
건립 이념이었습니다
that the calm smooth lines of rationalism are the cure for madness.
이성의 한계를 시험했던 괴델이
이곳에 오게 된 것은 아이러니입니다
Ironic then, that Godel driven mad by pushing the limits of rationalism
should come here to recover.
이성에 의한 확실성에 한계가 있음을
보여준 인물이 이곳에 있던 동안
But while the man who'd proved there was a limit to rational certainty was in the sanatorium.
바깥에서는 거대한 광기가
퍼져나가고 있었습니다
outside a greater madness was unfolding.
확실성을 부르짖는 선동가의 손에
온 나라가 힘을 실어주고 있었습니다
As a nation threw itself into the arms of a demagogue who promised there was certainty.
괴델의 정신병은 회복되었지만,
오스트리아는 그렇지 못했습니다
Godel's madness passed. Austria's didn't.
1939년 괴델은 나치 단원들에게
공격을 당하기까지 했고
In 1939, Godel himself was attacked by a group of Nazi thugs.
결국 같은 해에 마지못해
미국으로 떠났습니다
That same year he reluctantly left Austria for America.
전운이 감돌던 이 때에
또다른 젊은 천재가 등장합니다
It was during these pre-war years that another brilliant young man
앨런 튜링입니다
Alan Turing enters our story.
튜링은 전쟁 중
블레츨리 파크*에서
* 2차대전중 영국 암호 해독 부서의 애칭
Turing is most famous for his wartime work at Bletchley Park
독일의 이니그마* 암호를
해독한 것으로 유명합니다
* 독일군이 사용했던 기계식 암호
breaking the German Enigma code.
- 이니그마(수수께끼) -
그런데 그는
괴델의 불완전성 정리를
But he is also the man who made Godel's already devastating
더한층 나쁘게 확장시킨
사람이기도 합니다
incompleteness theorem even worse.
그는 괴델보다 더 실용적인
관점에서 접근했고
Turing was a much more practical man than Godel
괴델의 정리를 좀더 깔끔하게
표현하려고 했습니다
and simply wanted to make Godel's theorem clearer and simpler.
그 방법에 대한 연구는
새로운 통찰을 낳았습니다
How to do it came to him as he said later in a vision.
바로 '컴퓨터'입니다
That vision was the computer.
사실은, 오늘날 세상을 바꾼
컴퓨터의 발명도
The invention that has shaped the modern world was first imagined
다소 추상적이고 와닿지 않는
괴델의 불완전성 정리를
simply as the means to make Godel's incompleteness theorem more concrete
뚜렷하게 구체화하려고 노력하는
과정에서 생겨난 것입니다
because for many Godel's proof had simply been too abstract.
(괴델의 정리는) 수리철학적으로
매우 큰 타격입니다
It's an absolutely devastating result from a philosophical point of view.. we still haven't absorbed..
그러나 증명 자체는 피상적이어서,
구체적으로 어떤 함의가 있는지
but the proof was too superficial, it didn't get at the real heart of what was going on.
파악하기 어려웠습니다
It was more tantalizing than anything else.
그런 타격을 줄만한
이유라기엔 좀 약했달까요
It was not a good reason for something so devastating and fundamental.
그레고리 채이틴 - 수학자, IBM 연구소
괴델이 찾은 증명 불가능한 명제는
지나치게 교묘하게 조작해낸 것이라서
It was too clever by half, it was too superficial, it said "I'm unprovable.", you know.. so what?
실질적으로 얼마나 심각한 문제인지
감을 잡기가 어렵습니다
This doesn't give you any insight into how serious the problem is.
그런데 5년 후
튜링의 접근법이야말로
But Turing 5 years later his approach to incompleteness,
불완전성을 더 잘 이해하는
올바른 방향이었다고 봅니다
that I felt was getting more in the right direction.
튜링은 컴퓨터라는 관점에서
불완전성을 바라보았으며
Turing recast incompleteness in terms of computers
컴퓨터 또한
논리를 다루는 기계이므로
and showed that since they are logic machines,
불완전성은 컴퓨터가 풀지 못하는
문제가 존재함을 의미합니다
incompleteness meant there would always be some problems they would never solve.
그러한 문제를 입력하면
컴퓨터는 무한 루프에 빠지게 됩니다
A machine fed one of these problems would never stop.
설상가상으로, 튜링은
이러한 종류의 문제들을
And worse, Turing proved there was no way of telling beforehand
사전에 판별해내는 것은
불가능함을 증명했습니다
which these problems were.
괴델은 모든 논리 체계에
해결 불가능한 문제가 있음을 증명했습니다
Godel had proved that in all systems of logic there would be some unsolvable problems
이것만도 나쁜 뉴스인데
.. which is bad enough.
튜링은 불난 집에
기름을 끼얹었습니다
Then Turing comes along and makes matters much worse.
괴델까지만 해도, 증명 가능한 문제와
불가능한 문제를 구별할 방법만 있다면
At least with Godel, there was the hope that you could distinguish
between the provable and the unprovable,
증명 불가능한 문제는 회피할수 있는
일말의 가능성이 있었습니다
and simply leave the unprovable to one side.
그러나 어떤 문제가
증명 불가능한지의 여부를
What Turing does is prove that in fact there is no way of telling
판별하는 일반적인 방법은
없다는것을 튜링이 증명했습니다
which will be the unprovable problems.
유한한 단계 내에 판정이 된다는
보장이 없습니다
So how do you know when to stop?
주어진 문제가
단지 아주 어려운 것인지
You will never know whether the problem you're working on is simply extraordinarily difficult
애초에 증명이
불가능한것인지 말이죠
or if it's fundamentally unprovable.
이것이 튜링의
'정지(停止) 문제'입니다
And that is Turing's 'halting problem'.
튜링의 설명은
더 실제적인 방식입니다
But Turing makes it very down to earth because he talks about machines
어떤 기계를 설정하고, 그 실행이
종료되냐 아니냐에 대한 것이니까요
and he talks about whether a machine will halt or not.
그 논문에서는 딱히
그런 표현을 쓰지는 않았지만
It's there in his paper.. he didn't call it, didn't speak of it in those terms
기본 아이디어는 그렇습니다
but the ideas are really there in his original paper that's what I learnt.
손에 잡히는
컴퓨터에 대한 얘깁니다
And this sounds so concrete and down to earth, you know computers are physical devices
프로그램을 돌립니다,
별도의 입출력은 없는 프로그램이죠..
and you just start it running and there are two possibilities if you start a program running -
프로그램을 실행하면
결과는 둘 중 하나입니다
a self contained program running with no input/output, it's just there. It's running on a computer.
첫째, 언젠가는 실행을 종료하고
And one possibility is it's going to stop eventually saying
답을 내놓고 끝, 이렇게 되거나
it finishes the work, come up with an answer and stop, done, finished.
둘째, 답을 찾으려고
계속 실행하면서
The other possibility is it's going to be searching forever and never find what it's looking for,
영원히 종료하지 않는겁니다.
이렇게 둘 중 하나죠
never finish the calculation, just go on forever. It's one or the other.
정리하면, "프로그램 실행이
종료될지 아닌지 어떻게 알 수 있는가?"
The problem is: how can we tell that a program is never going to stop?
답은, "일반적인 판정 방법은 없다".
이것이 불완전성의 튜링 버전입니다
And the answer is: there's no systematic general way to do it,
and this is Turing's version of incompleteness.
튜링은 괴델의 불완전성으로부터
Turing gets incompleteness.. Godel's profound discovery..
'계산 불가능성'이라는
일반화시킨 개념을 만든 것이죠
he gets it as a corollary of something more basic which is 'uncomputability',
어떤 컴퓨터로도
계산할 수 없다는 성질입니다
things which cannot be calculated, things which no computer can calculate.
특정 영역에서는 '대부분'의
문제가 계산 불가능한데..
In certain domains, 'most' things cannot be calculated..
그게 선생님이 연구하시는거죠?
But that's your work isn't it? You come along and make it worse again..
- 더욱 '나쁜' 결과로 확장하는..
- 그냥 열심히 할 뿐이죠
- as if the news wasn't bad enough..
- I do my best..
그중 일부는 이미 튜링의 논문에도
있습니다. 그가 강조하진 않았지만..
Yes, I do my best. Some of it is already contained there in Turing's paper
although he doesn't emphasize it.
불완전성으로부터 착안한
튜링의 심오한 물음은
Startling as the halting problem was, the really profound part of incompleteness for Turing
컴퓨터가 아닌
우리의 정신에 관한 문제입니다
was not what it said about logic or computers, but what it said about us, and our minds.
인간의 두뇌는
과연 컴퓨터일까요?
Were we or weren't we computers?
그것은 튜링의 삶에서도
중요한 의미를 갖는 질문입니다
It was the question that went to the heart of who Turing was.
튜링에게는 각별히 사랑했던
대상이 둘 있었습니다
Turing was a man of two great loves.
첫째는 크리스토퍼 모컴이라는
남자였습니다
The first was for a young man, Christopher Morcom.
둘째는 그가 세상에 내놓은
컴퓨터입니다
The second was for the computer which he felt he had brought into this world.
크리스토퍼를 향한 사랑은
그에게 지울 수 없는 기억입니다
His love for Christopher had a unique place in his life.
그가 안타깝게도
요절했기 때문이죠
Because Christopher died tragically young.
그는 순수한 첫사랑을
영원히 잃었지만
Turing never recaptured that first pure love
그 추억을 지워버리지도 않았습니다
but never let go of the memory of what it had been.
그리고 컴퓨터라는
아이디어를 떠올린 뒤에는
But when Turing developed the idea of computer
커다란 잠재력을 지닌
컴퓨터와 사랑에 빠졌습니다
he began to fall in love in a very different way, with the sheer power of what he had imagined.
그는 언젠가 컴퓨터가
단순한 기계의 수준을 뛰어넘어
He fell in love with the fantastic idea that one day computers would be more than machines,
사람처럼 배우고 생각하는 존재가
될 수도 있다는 생각에 매혹되었습니다
they would be like children capable of learning, thinking and communicating.
또한 과학자의 통찰력을 발휘하여,
만일 인간의 정신도 컴퓨터와 같다면
And the scientist in him could also see that if our minds were like computers
컴퓨터가 우리 자신을 이해하는
훌륭한 도구라는 것을 깨달았습니다
then here in our hands was the means to understand ourselves.
칸토어에서 시작된 무한에 대한
순수 수학적인 질문은
What started with Cantor as a question from pure mathematics about the nature of infinity,
괴델에 의해 논리의 한계에 대한
질문이 되었고
in Godel's hands became a question about the limits of logic,
튜링은 이것을 우리 인간 자신의
정신에 대한 질문으로 바꾸었습니다
and now with Turing it comes into focus as a question about us, and the nature of our minds.
튜링을 계산주의자*로 보는
시각이 일반적입니다
* 인간의 두뇌가 본질적으로 컴퓨터와 동등한
정보 처리 시스템이라고 보는 심리학적 견해
There is this sort of standard view - Turing was a computationalist
로저 펜로즈 - 수학자, 옥스포드 대학
그가 그러한 입장을 취했던
시기가 분명히 있습니다
and certainly in certain stage of his life he did take that point of view.
인간의 두뇌를 모방한 기계를
만들 수도 있겠죠
Well maybe you can make one of these machines imitate the human mind.
하지만 그는 컴퓨터의 한계를
물론 잘 알고 있었습니다
But he was of course well aware of these limitations of computers
그것이 그의
주요 업적이기도 하구요
and that was one of his important results of his own.
그가 중간에 입장을
바꾸었을수도 있다고 봅니다
I think he may have shifted his view. He may have vacillated a bit
and had one view and then another.
그러다 컴퓨터를
실제로 구현한 이후에는
But then when he really developed the computers as actual machines
(계산주의가) 아마도 옳은 방향이라고
생각했을것도 같습니다
he sort of took off(???) and thought maybe these really are going to..
자신이 지지하는 과학 이론에
완전히 빠져들게 되면
it's a kind of.. when you get into a scientific thing you get totally..
"이것이 모든 문제를 풀 수 있는 답이야"
라고 생각하기 쉽죠
you think "maybe this is solving all problems".
그 이론에 이미 내재된 한계를
실감하지 못하고 말입니다
without realizing their limitations that are there, and which are part of his own theories.
튜링은 자신과 괴델의 연구의
의미를 알고 있었습니다
Turing understood that Godel's and his own work said that
즉, 인간의 두뇌가 컴퓨터라면
마찬가지로 불완전성의 적용 대상이므로
if our minds were computers then incompleteness would apply to us
따라서 논리학의 한계는
곧 인간 정신의 한계를 뜻하며
and the limitations of logic would be our limitations.
인간은 논리 추론의 한계를
초월할수 없다는 것을 말입니다
We would not be capable of leaps of imagination beyond logic.
사실, 튜링의 수학 이론이 그의
개인적 철학과 일치할 필요는 없죠
Turing's personality is one thing. His mathematics doesn't have to be consistent with his personality.
인공지능에 관한
그의 저작을 보면
There is his work on artificial intelligence where I think he does believe that
그는 기계도 인간처럼.. 더 낫든, 다르든,
어쨌든 '지능'을 가질수 있다고 믿었습니다
machines could become intelligent just like people or better or different but intelligent.
그런데, 첫번째 논문을 보면
기계의 한계를 지적하고 있습니다
But if you look at his first paper, when he points out that machines have limits
대부분의 수는 어떠한 기계로도
계산할수 없다는 증명을 통해서 말이죠
(수리논리학에서 말하는 '수를 계산한다'는
개념은 일상적으로 말하는 숫자 계산과 다름)
because there are numbers.. in fact most numbers cannot be calculated by any machine.
그러나, 튜링 자신이 벌써
He's showing the power of the human mind
기계의 한계를 초월하는
인간의 상상력을 과시하고 있죠
to imagine things that escape what any machine could ever do.
튜링의 철학적 견해와 상반되죠.
그가 스스로를 '기계'라고 생각했을지라도,
That may go against his own philosophy, he may think of himself as a machine..
그 자신이 바로 첫 논문에서부터
컴퓨터라는 개념을 창조해 내고
but his very first paper is smashing machines..
그것의 명백한 한계를
통렬하게 지적하고 있으니까요
it's creating machines.. and then it's pointing out their devastating limitations.
튜링도 이 딜레마를 알았지만
Turing was well aware of these problems
인간의 정신을 기계적 계산으로 환원하여
설명하는데 전력을 다했습니다
but desperately wanted to prove he could get the fullness of the human mind from mere computation.
그것은 과학자로서의
바람만은 아니었습니다
And it wasn't just the scientist in him that wanted to do this.
튜링이 늘 가졌던 신념은
위선과 기만,
Turing's personal philosophy which he stuck to all his life
비굴한 타협으로부터
자유로운 삶이었습니다
was to be free from hypocrisy, compromise and deceit.
튜링은 동성애자였고, 그때는
이것이 위험한 불법행위였습니다
Turing was a homosexual when it was both illegal and even dangerous.
그는 그것을 특별히 감추지도
드러내지도 않았습니다
Yet he never hid it, nor made it an issue.
컴퓨터는 거짓이나 위선을 모릅니다
With computers there are no lies or hypocrisy.
우리가 컴퓨터였다면, 우리는
튜링이 원했던 모습의 존재였을겁니다
If we were computers then we were the kind of creature Turing wanted us to be.
누구나 마음을 바꿀 수 있죠.
자신의 생각을 돌아보고
People could vacillate. They could have one view and then wonder about this,
이게 정말 맞는걸까 되묻거나
다른 생각으로 갈아타기도 하죠
"Is this really right?" and then have another view and play around,
좋은 과학자라면 무턱대고
하나의 관점에만 집착하지 않아요
If they're good scientists, they will do that. They won't just doggedly follow one point of view.
그래서 저는 튜링의 마음도
흔들리지 않았을까 합니다
So I suspect Turing vacillated rather.
하지만 제 생각에
튜링은 자신의 관점에 대한..
But I think in a lot of his analyses and criticisms of
.. 다른이들의 비판을
분석하고 허점을 찾아내서
other people who criticized his view
이렇게 반박하려
했을수도 있죠
he would show the flaws in their arguments and say,
"계산 불가능성에 대한
정리에도 불구하고.."
"Well look, it may still be, despite all these theorems we know about non-computability, .."
"..논증에서 이러이러한
빠져나갈 구멍이 있으니까.."
"..it still might be that we are computational entities."
"..어쨌든 인간의 정신은
컴퓨터와 동등한 것일수도 있다."
and then point out "well, because of this and this loophole" and so on.
이런 빠져나갈 구멍만 있어도
스스로 만족했는지도 모릅니다
And maybe he came to believe those loopholes were sufficient to get him out.
또 튜링 머신*보다 강력한
오라클 머신**에 대한 연구도 했습니다
* 튜링 머신 = 튜링이 제안한 계산의 수학적 모델.
컴퓨터의 핵심 개념을 추상화시킨 것으로 보면 됨
But yet he did do these things like looking at oracle machines which were sort of super Turing machines
우리가 접할 수 있는
보통 컴퓨터와는 다른것이죠
** 오라클 머신 = 튜링 머신에 가상적인
능력을 추가시킨 것. 수학적 분석에 쓰임
and beyond them they're not machines that you could see anywhere constructing out of ordinary stuff.
이론적인 개념일 뿐이지만
But nevertheless as a theoretical entity
일반적인 컴퓨터의
능력을 넘는 이론적 기계입니다
these devices were theoretical things that would go beyond standard computers.
튜링은 이렇게 인간과
계산 기계 사이에서 갈등했습니다
This tension between the human and the computational was central to Turing's life.
이윽고 그를 죽음에 이르게 한
사건이 터졌습니다
And he lived with it until the events which led to his death.
전쟁 후 튜링은 국가정보부의
주시 대상이 되었습니다
After the war, Turing increasingly found himself drawing the attention of the Security Services.
냉전 하에서 동성애는
부도덕한 불법 행위일뿐 아니라
In the Cold War, homosexuality was seen as not only illegal and immoral
안보에 대한 위협으로
간주되었기 때문입니다
but also a security risk.
튜링은 1952년 3월 동성애 행위로
체포되어 유죄판결을 받았고
So when in March 1952 he was arrested, charged and found guilty of engaging in a homosexual act
당국은 그를 교정이 필요한
문제 인물로 지목했습니다
the authorities decided he was a problem that needed to be fixed.
여성 호르몬 에스트로겐을 주사하여
화학적 거세를 시도했습니다
They would chemically castrate him by injecting him with the female hormone, estrogen.
튜링은 인간이 아닌
기계 취급을 당한 것입니다
Turing was being treated as no more than a machine,
성 정체성의 불확실성 및
안보와 질서에 대한 위협을 제거하려고
chemically reprogrammed to eliminate the uncertainty of his sexuality
화학적으로 다시 프로그램된
기계 말입니다
and the risk they felt it posed to security and order.
이 요법은 끔찍하게도
그의 몸과 마음을 망가뜨렸습니다
To his horror he found the treatment affected his mind and his body.
유방이 부풀어올랐고
정신상태는 불안정해졌습니다
He grew breasts, his moods altered and he worried about his mind.
언제나 바르게 살았던 그에게는
For a man who'd always been authentic and at one with himself
'위선'이라는 주사를
맞은 것이나 다름없었습니다
it was as if he had been injected with hypocrisy.
1954년 6월 7일
튜링은 사망했습니다
On the 7th June 1954, Turing was found dead.
몇 입 깨문 사과가
그의 곁에 놓여 있었습니다
At his bedside an apple from which he had taken several bites.
튜링이 스스로 청산가리를
사과에 주입한 것입니다
Turing had poisoned the apple with cyanide.
튜링은 떠났지만,
그의 물음은 남았습니다
Turing was dead, but his question was not.
인간은 컴퓨터처럼 한계가 있는가,
아니면 논리의 한계를 넘을수 있는가?
Whether the mind was a computer and so limited by logic, or somehow able to transcend logic
이 물음은 이제
괴델의 고민이 되었습니다
was now the question that came to trouble the mind of Kurt Godel.
괴델은 이때 미국으로 와
고등과학원에 있었고
Godel was now working in America at the Institute for Advanced Study
지나칠 정도로 열심히
연구에 매달렸습니다
where he continued to work as obsessively as he ever had.
물론 이때의 괴델은
정신병에서 회복되었지만
Of course, Godel recovered from his time in the sanatorium.
이곳에서의 그는
아주 유별난 사람이었다고 합니다
But by the time he got here to the Institute for Advanced Study in America
he was a very peculiar man.
한 예로 소문에 의하면
One of the stories they tell about him is
사람이 많은 곳에서는
타인과 신체 접촉을 꺼려하여
if he was caught in the commons with a crowd of other people, he so hated physical contact
가만히 선 채로
쏙 빠져나갈 길을 찾은 다음
that he would stand very still so as to plot the perfect course out
누구와도 부딪치지 않고
지나갔다고 합니다
so as not to have to actually touch anyone.
냉난방 장치에서 나오는
'나쁜 공기'에
He also felt he was being poisoned by what he called 'bad air'
자신이 중독되고 있다고 느꼈으며
from heating systems and air conditioners
심지어 자기의 음식에
독이 들었다고 생각했습니다
and most of all he thought his food was being poisoned.
아내에게 모든 음식을
먼저 시식해달라고 했고
He insisted his wife taste all his food for him.
한번은 오렌지를 주문한 다음
독이 들었다며 반품하기도 했습니다
He would sometimes order oranges and then send them straight back claiming they were poisoned.
기인이 되어 버렸지만
그의 천재성은 죽지 않았습니다
Peculiar as Godel was, his genius was undimmed.
튜링과 달리, 괴델은
인간이 컴퓨터라고 믿지 않았습니다
Unlike Turing, Godel could not believe we were like computers.
그는 인간이 논리학의 한계를
어떻게 뛰어넘을수 있는지
He wanted to show how the mind had a way of reaching truth outside logic
또는 그렇지 못한다면 어떻게 될지
알아내려고 했습니다
and what it would mean if it couldn't.
이론상, 주어진 공리들로부터
기계적인 과정으로
In principle you could have a machine grinding away deducing all the consequences
모든 논리적 귀결을
생성할수 있다고 상상해 보면,
of a fixed set of principles.
수학은 생명력이 없는
정적인 세계일겁니다
And mathematics would be static and dead.
정리를 유도하는
기계적인 과정이 전부라면
It would just be a question of mechanically deducing all the consequences.
결국 수학자도
일종의 기계에 불과하죠
And so mathematicians in a sense would just be machines.
제 생각엔, 튜링은
스스로를 기계라고 생각했습니다
I mean Turing did think that he was a machine. I think he did.
'흉내내기 게임'*에 관한 논문으로
미루어 알 수 있죠
* 인공 지능을 판별하는 테스트.
지금은 '튜링 테스트'라고 부름
And I think that paper on the imitation game shows that.
괴델은 스스로를
기계로 간주하지 않았고
And Godel clearly did not think that he was a machine.
인간에게는 어떤 신성한
창의성이 있기 때문에
He thought that he was divine and that human beings have a divine spark in them
새로운 수학을
창조해낼 수 있다고 믿었죠
that enables them to create new mathematics I think.
인간만이 지닌 창의성을
그가 확신했던 까닭은 무엇일까요?
Why was Godel so convinced humans had this spark of creativity?
그것은 그의 절친한 친구
한 명과 공감했던
The key to his belief comes from a deep conviction he shared
어떤 철학적 확신에서
기인합니다
with one of the few close friends he ever had.
고등과학원에 있었던
또다른 오스트리아인 천재
That other Austrian genius who had settled at the Institute,
알베르트 아인슈타인입니다
Albert Einstein.
아인슈타인은 괴델과 함께
산책하는 특권을 누리고 싶어서
Einstein used to say that he came here to the Institute for Advanced Studies
고등과학원으로 온 것이라고
말하곤 했습니다
simply for the privilege of walking home with Kurt Godel.
판이한 이 두 사람이
친밀했던 이유는 무엇일까요?
And what was it that held this most unlikely of couples together?
아저씨처럼 푸근한 아인슈타인과
On the one had you've got the warm and avuncular Einstein
재미없고 야윈 내성적인 괴델.
and on the other the rather cold, wizened and withdrawn Kurt Godel.
저는 아인슈타인이 했던
이 말에 주목합니다
And the answer comes I think from something else that Einstein said.
"신(神)은 이해하기 까다롭지만,
심술궂은 존재는 아니다."
He said that God may be subtle but he's not malicious.
이것은 비유적인 표현으로,
What does that mean? Well, it means for Einstein is that
우주가 아무리 복잡해 보이더라도
반드시 아름다운 법칙이 있다는 말입니다
however complicated the universe might be, there will always be beautiful rules by which it works.
괴델의 철학도 같았습니다,
다시 말하면
Godel believed the same idea from his point of view to mean that
신은 인간에게 절대 불가해한 세상을
창조하지는 않았다는 것입니다
God would never have put us into a creation that we could then not understand.
그런데, 논리적 증명의 한계를
밝혀낸 괴델 자신이 어떻게
The question is, how is it that Kurt Godel can believe that God isn't malicious, that it's all understandable?
신이 심술궂지 않으며, 세상은
이해할수 있는 것이라고 믿었을까요?
Because Godel is the man who's proved that some things cannot be proven logically and rationally.
신은 사악하다고 했어야
하지 않을까요?
So surely God must be malicious?
그 답은, 아인슈타인처럼 괴델도
직관의 가치를 높이 샀기 때문일겁니다
The way he gets out of it is Godel, like Einstein, believed deeply in intuition
인간이 가진 직관의 힘으로
논리의 한계를 넘을수 있다는 것입니다
that we can know things outside of logic because we just intuit them.
탁월한 직관의 순간을 경험했던
두 사람 모두, 그 점을 믿었습니다
And they believed it because they have both felt it. They've both had their moments of intuition.
칸토어처럼 말이죠
Just like Cantor had had his.
그가 제안한
수학자의 행동 원리는..
He talks about new principles that the mathematician,
눈을 감고,
자아를 세상과 단절시키고,
closing your eyes, tuning out the real world,
수학적 직관력을 이용하여 직접
플라톤적 이데아의 세계를 인식하고
you can try to perceive directly by your mathematical intuition the Platonic world of ideas
거기서 이끌어낸 새로운 원리로
and come up with new principles which you can then use
수학을 발전시키는 것입니다
to extend the current set of principles in mathematics.
이렇게 괴델은 불완전성 정리가
인간의 한계를 뜻하지 않으며
And he viewed this as a way of getting around the limitations of his own theorem.
인간이 만들수 있는 수학의 한계는
없다고 생각했다고, 저는 판단합니다
I don't think he thought there was any limit to the mathematics that human beings were capable of.
이 주장을 입증할수 있을까요?
But how do you prove this?
카를 지그문트 - 수학자, 비엔나 대학
괴델 자신도 컴퓨터의 한계라는
해석을 끌어냈습니다
There's a interpretation that Godel himself drew. It was that computers are limited.
그는 인간 정신이 컴퓨터를
초월한다는 사실을 밝혀내려고
He certainly tried again and again to work out that
끊임없이 시도했습니다
the human mind transcends the computer
컴퓨터 프로그램으로
증명하기 어려운 진리도
in the sense that he can understand things to be true
그는 이해할 수 있었으니까요
that cannot be proved by a computer program.
괴델은 경험이나
수학적 논증보다는
Godel also was wrestling with finding means of knowledge
직관을 통해 진리를 추구하는
방법에 대해 고민했습니다
which are not based on experience and on mathematical reasoning
but on some sort of intuition.
그는 자신의 이론을 잘못 이해한
사람들에게 실망했습니다
The frustration for Godel was getting anyone to understand him.
어째서인지 많은 사람들이
괴델의 의도를 오해하고 있습니다
I think people very often, for some reason, misunderstand Godel, certainly his intention.
괴델은 사려깊은 방식으로
Godel was deliberately trying to show that
그가 생각하는 의미의
수학적 직관을 놓고
what one might call mathematical intuition, I here refer to what he called mathematical intuition
직관은 형식적인 규칙만 따라가는
추론의 범주 밖에 있음을
and he was demonstrating, clearly in my mind, demonstrated
보여주려고 했습니다
that this is outside just following formal rules.
어떤이들은 괴델의 말을
엉뚱하게 곡해해서
And I don't know, some people picked up on what he did and said,
"증명불가능한 진리가 존재하며, 이것들은
인간 정신이 닿을수 없는 영역에 있다."
"Well he's shown there are unprovable results and therefore beyond the mind."
이렇게들 말하는데, 원래 의미는,
어떤 논리 체계를 채택하더라도..
What he really showed was that for any system that you adopt,
아, 그리고 그 체계를
인간이 정했지만
which in a sense the mind has been removed from it
정해 놓은 다음에는
정신과는 별개의 문제이죠..
because your mind is used to lay down the system,
어쨌든 여기서부터,
"이 체계의 범위가 어디까지이냐?"
but from there on it takes over and you ask what's it's scope.
괴델의 답은, 어느 체계에든
반드시 한계가 있고
And what Godel showed is that it's scope is always limited and that the mind can go beyond it.
그러나 인간 정신은
그 제약에서 자유롭다는 겁니다
괴델은 모든 논리 체계에는 그 안에
증명 불가능한 명제가 있음을 증명했습니다
Here's the man who has said certain things cannot be proved within any rational and logical system.
그리고 인간에겐 직관이 있으니
그 제한이 문제가 되지 않는다고 했습니다
But he says that doesn't matter because the human mind isn't limited that way. We have Intuition.
그런데 이 설명이 말이 되려면
'직관'이라는 존재를 입증해야 하는데
But then of course, the one thing he really must prove to other people is the existence of intuition.
그것이 결코 쉬울리가 없죠
The one thing you'll never be able to prove.
그가 자신의 견해를 강하게 주장했던
논문 초안이 있는데
He has these drafts of papers where he expresses himself very strongly
괴델 자신도 불만족스러워했습니다
but he wasn't satisfied with that,
창의성이나 직관 같은건
증명할수가 없기 때문이죠
because he couldn't prove a theorem about creativity or intuition.
그냥 '감'에 불과하니까요
It was just a gut feeling that he had.. and he wasn't satisfied with that.
칸토어가 그랬듯이
And so Godel, like Cantor before him,
괴델도 어떻게든 풀고 싶지만
풀수없는 문제에 부딪쳤습니다
had finally found a problem he desperately wanted to solve but could not.
쉽게 빠져나올수 없는
논리의 쳇바퀴에 갇혀 버렸습니다
He was now caught in a loop, a logical paradox from which his mind could not escape.
동시에 스스로를 서서히
굶겨 죽이기 시작했습니다
And at the same time he slowly starved himself to death.
수학의 한계를 수학을 이용하여
입증한다는건 일면 이율배반적이죠
Using mathematics to show the limits of mathematics is psychologically very contradictory.
괴델도 분명히
이것을 잘 알고 있었습니다
It's clear in Godel's case that he appreciated this.
그 자신의 삶도 역설적이었죠
His own life has this paradox.
대상으로 그 대상 자신을
분석하는 일입니다
What Godel is, is the mind thinking about itself and what it can achieve at the deepest level.
누군가는 '현대의 현기증'이라고
표현했던 것인데
Someone used the phrase 'the vertigo of the modern'.
그런 재귀적인 소용돌이 속으로
빠져드는 것입니다
You can be led into that particular reflexive whirlpool
루이스 새스 - 임상심리학자, 럿거스 대학
생각에 대해 생각하는 것에 대해
생각하는 것에 대해 생각하는..
where you begin to think about thinking about thinking about thinking..
자기만의 생각 속에
말려드는 것이죠
and you find yourself entangled in your own thoughts.
저는 이것이 현대(現代)의
본질이 아닌가 생각합니다
Well, that seems to me almost the quintessence of the modern moment.
'자기 관찰의 역설'이라고
부를만한 것이니까요
because there you have.. what you could call a 'paradox of self-reflection'.
모더니즘과 연관되어 있는
종류의 광기는
The kind of madness that you find associated with modernism is a kind of madness
이성적 활동에서
기인하는 것 뿐만 아니라
that's' bound up with not only rationality but with all the paradoxes that arise
자의식, 그러니까
의식적인 자아를 스스로 관찰하고
from self-consciousness, from the consciousness contemplating it's own being as consciousness,
논리 자체를 논리로써
분석하는데서 나오는 역설입니다
or from logic contemplating it's own being as logic.
그 자신이 논리의 한계를
밝히긴 했지만
Even though he's shown that logic has certain limitations
그래도 여전히 합리성과 논리를
중시했기 때문에
he's still so drawn to that to the significance of the rational and logical
논리적으로 중요한 결과를
증명하려고 사력을 다했습니다
that he desperately wants to prove whatever is most important logically
논리가 아닌
다른 대안이라도 말이죠
even if it's an alternative to logic.
논리적 증명에 대한
집착으로부터
How strange.. and what a testimony to his inability to separate himself
괴델 자신이 자유롭지
못했다는 반증입니다
to detach himself from the need for logical proof. Godel of all people.
우리 이야기의 처음에서,
칸토어는 수학의 맨 밑바닥에
At the beginning of our story, Cantor had hoped that at its deepest level
'신의 마음'인 확실성이
자리하고 있을거라 믿었습니다
mathematics would rest on certainties which for him were the mind of God.
그러나 의도와는 다르게
불확실성을 들추어냈고
But instead, he had uncovered uncertainties
튜링과 괴델은 이것이
사라지지 않을것임을 증명했습니다
which Turing and Godel then proved would never go away.
불확실성은 수학과 논리의 토대를
이루는 피할 수 없는 존재입니다
They were an inescapable part of the very foundations of math and logic.
확실성의 세계를 지배하는
완벽한 논리가 있을 것이라는
The almost religious belief that there was a perfect logic
거의 종교에 가까운 믿음은
깨어졌습니다
which governed a world of certainties had unravelled itself.
논리의 한계가
논리에 의해 드러났고
Logic had revealed the limitations of logic.
확실성을 향한 추구에서
불확실성이 드러났습니다
The search for certainty had revealed uncertainty.
다른 사람들이
어떻게 생각할지 모르지만
There's a fashionable solution to the problem
제가 생각하는
하나의 해법은 뭐냐면
which is basically in my opinion people might hate me for this
잘 안보이게
살짝 덮어두는 것입니다
is sweeping it under the carpet. But you see the problem is
그런데 이건 문제를
푸는건 아니죠
I don't think you want to solve the problem.
사실, 문제를 끼고 사는게
더 재미있지 않겠어요?
I think it's much more fun to live with the problem.
창의성의 여지가 있잖아요
It's much more creative.
절대적 확실성이라..
인간의 삶에 그런건 없습니다
This notion of absolute certainty.. there is no absolute certainty in human life.
세상에 대해 우리가
가질 수 있는 지식은
But our knowledge.. our possible knowledge of this world of ideas
불완전하고 유한합니다.
우리가 그러한 존재이니까요
can only be incomplete and finite because we're incomplete and finite.
오늘날에도, 어떤 지식들은
너무 위험한 것이라고 여겨집니다
The problem is that today some knowledge still feels too dangerous.
칸토어, 볼츠만, 괴델의 시대에서
별로 달라진게 없는듯도 합니다
Because our times are not so different to Cantor or Boltzmann or Godel's time.
우리들도 역시,
굳게 믿었던 대상은 도전받고
We too feel things we thought were solid being challenged,
확실성은 미끄러져 나갑니다
feel our certainties slipping away.
예전과 다름없이 우리는
확실성에 대한 믿음을 꼭 쥐고
And so, as then, we still desperately want to cling to a belief in certainty.
위안을 얻으려 합니다
It makes us feel safe.
제 생각에
우리에게 남겨진 질문은
At the end of this journey, the question I think we are left with
칸토어나 볼츠만의 때와
다르지 않습니다
is actually the same as it was in Cantor and Boltzmann's time.
지금 우리는 불확실성과 함께
살아갈수 있을만큼 성숙할까요?
Are we grown up enough to live with uncertainties?
아니면 우리는 지난 세기의
실수를 되풀이하며
Or will we repeat the mistakes of the 20th century
맹목적으로 또다른 확실성을
찾고 있는 것일까요?
and pledge blind allegiance to yet another certainty?
딕테이션, 한/영 자막 제작
DCinside 과학갤/다큐갤 '디핑'
croydon.egloos.com